# Personal Information

Name Sebastian Contreras

Date of Birth April 29th, 1993

Mobile +49 177 7708678

Email sebastian.contreras@ds.mpg.de

Current affiliation Max Planck Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization

ORCID https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8909-774X

SCOPUS ID 57212808478



## Short bio

Sebastian Contreras studied engineering at Universidad de Chile (Chile), and received his Master's degree in 2019. He joined the Neural Systems Theory Group in 2020 as a PhD student, working on disease spread and COVID-19. Using different tools from formal analysis, he searches to uncover general principles in the dynamics of disease spread and its interaction between pandemic and infodemic. With his work, he provided basic understanding of the pandemic that was not only reflected in high-impact publications, but also found its way to public knowledge, especially on tipping point of disease spread dynamics.

## Education

Jul. 2020 - Present

### Ph.D. candidate in Physics

International Max Planck Research School, Georg-August-Universität, Göttingen, Germany

Jul. 2017 – Jul. 2019

### Master of Sciences (Metallurgy)

Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile: 7.0/7.0

Mar. 2012 – Jul. 2017

#### Mining Engineering

Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile: 7.0/7.0

# Awards and academic recognition

### 2020 Best Graduate (2019)

Colegio de Ingenieros de Chile (Chile Engineers Association).

#### 2018 **Outstanding student**

Master's Program, Faculty of Physical and Mathematical Sciences (FCFM), Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile.

## Academic Experience

Jun. 2020 - Present Max Planck Institute for Dynamics and Self-Organization - MPRG Priesemann Research Assistant/PhD Student

- Modelling the challenges of containing SARS-CoV-2 via Test-Trace-and-Isolate.
- Designing long-term pandemic control strategies: metaestable equilibrium at low case
- Modelling the effect of vaccines the spreading dynamics of COVID-19.
- Modelling the interplay between information, behavior, and disease spread.
- Competition-Coinfection dynamics of concurrent diseases and variants thereof.

Jun. 2016 – Jun. 2020 **Centre** 

Biotechnology and Bioengineering, CeBiB Santiago, Chile, https://www.cebib.cl/- Research Assistant and Researcher (Math. Modeling Group)

- Modelling the spreading dynamics of COVID-19 in Chile with a multigroup SEIRA model.
- Developing real-time estimators of the effective reproduction number of COVID-19  $R_t$ .

(2016-2020) Project: Parametric definition of health in human Glucose-Insulin dynamics. Development of a novel DDE model for the human glucose-insulin dynamics and tailored inverse problem-solving techniques for parameter recognition.

(2018-2020) **Project:** DMAKit: A user-friendly web platform and Python library for bringing state-of-the-art data analysis techniques to non-specific users.

Jul. 2017 - Jul. 2019 Laboratory for Rheology and Fluid dynamics (LRF) Santiago, Chile - Researcher

- Statistical characterization of floc-structures in flocculation of clays, using graphene oxide-doped flocculants, for optimizing water recovery in mineral processing plants.
- Characterization of the effect of mineralogy, clay abundance and electrolyte concentration in the rheological properties of copper sulfide tailings.
- Development of statistically-based methodology for variability assessment of rheological parameters in mineral processing.

# Teaching Experience

Jul. 2013 - Jul. 2019 Universidad de Chile Santiago, Chile - Teaching Assistant, Lecturer

- Ordinary Differential Equations, undergraduate course with  $\sim\!100$  students per semester.
- Mathematical Methods in Engineering, obligatory course for the Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering program.
- Dynamics of Hyper-Concentrated Suspensions (non-Newtonian fluid dynamics), optional course for the Ph.D. in Fluid Dynamics program.

# Skills & Background Knowledge

## Programs and Programming Languages

Matlab Programming, Advanced

LATEX, Advanced

Python Programming, Intermediate

Julia Programming, Basic

# Languages

Spanish, Native

English, *Fluent* 

German, *Intermediate* (B1), aiming for C1 by the end of my Ph.D.

# Hobbies (I can bring much more than science!)

Hiking-Trekking I love outdoors and exploring in Chile (Tierra del Fuego, Torres del Paine, Patagonia, Atacama Desert, Easter Island), or around the world.

**Sports** Running, swimming, diving, climbing, basically anything outdoors.

Music I play the piano and sing, and before dedicating my life to science, I played the Cello professionally.

Cooking I know many Chilean, Peruvian, and German recipes that might be worth trying!

## Indexed Publications

- 2022 Medina-Ortiz, D., Contreras, S., Amado-Hinojosa, J., Almonacid-Torres, J., Navarrete, M., Asenjo, J. & Olivera-Nappa, A. "Combination of digital signal processing and assembled predictive models facilitates the rational design of proteins". *Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences* 9:898627. doi: 10.3389/fmolb.2022.898627
- 2022 <u>Contreras, S.</u>, Dehning, J., & Priesemann, V. "Describing a landscape we are yet discovering". *In press* in **AStA Advances in Statistical Analysis**. doi: 10.1007/s10182-022-00449-5
- 2022 Olivera-Nappa, A.\*, <u>Contreras, S.\*</u>, Tevy, MF., Medina-Ortiz, D., Leschot, A., Vigil, P., & Conca, C. "Patient-wise methodology to assess glycemic health status: applications to quantify the efficacy and physiological targets of polyphenols on glycemic control". *Frontiers in Nutrition* 9:831696. doi: 10.3389/fnut.2022.831696
- Dönges, P.\*, Wagner, J.\*, Contreras, S.\*, Iftekhar, EN.\*, Bauer, S., Mohr, SB., Dehning, J., Calero Valdéz, A., Kretzschmar, M., Mäs, M., Nagel, K., & Priesemann, V. "Interplay between risk perception, behaviour, and COVID-19 spread". *Frontiers in Physics* 10:842180. doi: 10.3389/fphy.2022.842180
- Oróstica, KY., Contreras, S.\*, Sánchez-Daza, A., Fernandez, J., Priesemann, V., & Olivera-Nappa, A. "New year, new SARS-CoV-2 variant: resolutions on genomic surveillance protocols to face Omicron". *The Lancet Regional Health Americas* 7, 100203. doi: 10.1016/j.lana.2021.100203
- 2022 <u>Contreras, S.</u>, Olivera-Nappa, Á., & Viola Priesemann "Rethinking COVID-19 vaccine allocation: it is time to care about our neighbours.". *The Lancet Regional Health–Europe* 12, 100277. doi: 10.1016/j.lanepe.2021.100277
- 2022 Sanchez-Daza, A., Medina-Ortiz, D., Olivera-Nappa, Á., & Contreras, S. "COVID-19 modeling under uncertainty: Statistical data analysis for unveiling true spreading dynamics and guiding correct epidemiological management". Book chapter in Springer Series Studies in Systems, Decision and Control. doi: 10.1007/978-3-030-72834-2\_9
- 2021 <u>Contreras, S.</u>, Dehning, J., Mohr, SB., Spitzner, FP., Bauer, S. & Priesemann, V. "Low case numbers enable long-term stable pandemic control without lockdowns". *Science Advances* 7(41): eabg2243. doi: 10.1126/sciadv.abg2243
- 2021 Bauer, S.\*, Contreras, S.\*, Dehning, J., Linden, M., Iftehar, E. Mohr, SB., Olivera-Nappa, Á, & Priesemann, V. "Relaxing restrictions at the pace of vaccination increases freedom and guards against further COVID-19 waves in Europe". *PLoS Computational Biology*17(9): e1009288. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1009288
- 2021 Contreras, S. & Priesemann, V. "Risking further COVID-19 waves despite vaccination". *The Lancet Infectious Diseases* 21(6), 745-746 (2021) doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(21)00167-5
- 2021 <u>Contreras, S.</u>, Dehning, J., Loidolt, M., Spitzner, FP., Urrea-Quintero, J., Mohr, SB., Wilczek, M., Zierenberg, J., Wibral, M., & Priesemann, V. "The challenges of containing SARS-CoV-2 via test-trace-and-isolate". *Nature Communications* 12(2021) 371. doi: 10.1038/s41467-020-20699-8
- 2020 Contreras, S., Biron-Lattes, J. P., Villavicencio, H. A., Medina-Ortiz, D., Llanovarced-Kawles, N., & Olivera-Nappa, A. "Statistically-based methodology for correcting delay-induced errors on the evaluation of COVID-19 pandemic". *Chaos, Solitons & Fractals* 139(2020), 110087. doi: 10.1016/j.chaos.2020.110087
- 2020 Contreras, S., Villavicencio, H. A., Medina-Ortiz, D., Biron-Lattes, J. P., & Olivera-Nappa, A. "A multi-group SEIRA model for the spread of COVID-19 among heterogeneous populations". Chaos, Solitons & Fractals 136(2020), 109925. doi: 10.1016/j.chaos.2020.109925

- 2020 Medina-Ortiz, D., Contreras, S., Quiroz, C., & Olivera-Nappa, A. "DMAKit: A user-friendly web platform for bringing state-of-the-art data analysis techniques to non-specific users". *Information Systems* 93(2020), 101557. doi: 10.1016/j.is.2020.101557
- 2020 <u>Contreras, S.</u>, Castillo, C., Olivera-Nappa, A., & Ihle, C.F. "A new statistically-based methodology for variability assessment of rheological parameters in mineral processing". *Minerals Engineering* 156(2020), 106494. doi: 10.1016/j.mineng.2020.106494
- 2020 Contreras, S., Villavicencio, H. A., Medina-Ortiz, D., Saavedra, C. P., & Olivera-Nappa, A. "Real-time estimation of Rt for supporting public-health policies against COVID-19". *Frontiers in Public Health* 8, 556689. doi: 10.3389/fpubh.2020.556689
- 2020 Medina-Ortiz, D., <u>Contreras, S.</u>, Barrera-Saavedra, Y., Cabas-Mora, G., & Olivera-Nappa, A. "Country-Wise Forecast Model for the Effective Reproduction Number Rt of Coronavirus Disease". *Frontiers in Physics* 8, 304. doi: 10.3389/fphy.2020.00304
- 2020 <u>Contreras, S.</u>, Medina-Ortiz, D., Conca, C., & Olivera-Nappa, A. "A novel synthetic model of the glucose-insulin system for a patient-wise inference of parameters from small size OGTT data". *Frontiers in Bioengineering and Biotechnology* 8, 195. doi: 10.3389/fbioe.2020.00195
- 2020 Medina-Ortiz, D., Contreras, S., Quiroz, C., & Olivera-Nappa, A. "Development of supervised learning predictive models for highly non-linear biological, biomedical and general datasets".
  Frontiers in Molecular Biosciences 7, 13. doi: 10.3389/fmolb.2020.00013
- 2019 Contreras, S., Ihle, C., & Palza, H. "FBRM measurements of fine solid flocculation performance using graphene oxide-doped industrial flocculants in high-clay tailings". *In Proceedings of the 29th Int. Mineral Processing Congress*.

# Submitted Manuscripts

Oróstica, KY.\*, Contreras, S.\*, Mohr, SB., Dehning, J., Medina-Ortiz, D., Bauer, S., ..., & Priesemann, V. "Mutational signatures and transmissibility of SARS-CoV-2 Gamma and Lambda variants". https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.10018.

# Editorial work

Reviewer Journal referee for The Lancet Infectious Diseases (1), IEEE Communications Magazine (2), The Lancet Regional Health - Europe (2), PLoS Computational Biology (2), PLoS ONE (2), Mathematical Medicine and Biology (2) Chaos, Solitons & Fractals (8), Communications Physics (2), Communications Medicine (1), Scientific Reports (6), Heliyon (3), Computers in Biology and Medicine (6), Frontiers in Medicine (1), BMC Bioinformatics (2) and Frontiers

in Public Health (3). I have also reviewed book chapters (2) in the Studies in Systems, Decision and Control Springer series.

# Academic references

### Dr. Viola Priesemann

Max Planck Research Group Leader, MPI for Dynamics and Self-Organization viola.priesemann@ds.mpg.de

### Prof. Dr. hc. Carlos Conca

Full Professor, Department of Mathematical Engineering and Center for Mathematical Modeling, Universidad de Chile cconca@ing.uchile.cl

### Prof. Dr. Patricio Aceituno

Emeritus Professor, Department of Geophysics, Universidad de Chile aceituno@dgf.uchile.cl

## Prof. Dr. Álvaro Olivera-Nappa

Principal researcher (Math. Modeling & Protein Engineering), CeBiB, and Assistant Professor, Department of Chemical Engineering, Biotechnology and Materials, Universidad de Chile aolivera@ing.uchile.cl

# Conference attendances

### International conferences

- 2021 Speaker in the I Madeira COVID-19 Modellers Encounter. 27 September 2 October 2021, Madeira, Portugal. Spreading dynamics of COVID-19: Compartmental models and beyond (eng)
- 2019 Speaker in the 6th International Seminar on Tailings Management, Tailings 2019, Santiago, Chile. Oral presentation: Characterization of the effect of clay mineralogy and content on the rheological behavior of copper sulfide tailings (eng).
- 2018 Speaker in the 29th International Mineral Processing Congress, 17-21 September 2018, Moscow, Russia. Oral presentation: Characterization of the effect of clay mineralogy and content on the rheological behavior of copper sulfide tailings (eng).

### National conferences

- 2021 Speaker in the XIII Workshop CeBiB: Metabolic Engineering, Bioinformatics and Genomics for Biotechnological Applications. 29 June, 1-2 July 2021, online. *Spreading Dynamics of Infectious Diseases: A Tale of Tipping-Points* (eng)
- 2019 Poster presentation in the XI Workshop CeBiB: Metabolic Engineering, Bioinformatics and Genomics for Biotechnological Applications. 27-29 November 2019, Hotel Termas de Puyehue, Los Lagos Region, Chile. Poster: DMAKit, a user-friendly web platform for bringing state-of-the-art data analysis techniques to non-specific users (eng).
- 2019 Speaker in the X Workshop CeBiB: Metabolic Engineering, Bioinformatics and Genomics for Biotechnological Applications. 29-31 July 2019, Sheraton Hotel, Santiago, Chile. Oral presentation: Mathematical modeling and data mining: Applications and tool development (spa).
- 2017 Speaker in the VII Workshop CeBiB: Metabolic Engineering, Bioinformatics and Genomics for Biotechnological Applications. 29 November - 1 December 2017, Hotel Antofagasta, Antofagasta Region, Chile. Oral presentation: Mathematical modeling of the human glucoseinsulin system (eng).
- 2017 Attended to the XIV Congress on Pipeline of Concentrate, Slurry, Tailings and Water. 23-24 November 2019, Hotel Sheraton Miramar, Valparaiso Region, Chile.